# Joshua T. Abbott

### Profile

Computational social scientist with expertise in user modeling, Bayesian statistics, and representation learning. I use theory and large-scale experiments from psychological sciences to build better machine learning models for information retrieval and recommendation systems.

Interested in both data science and machine learning research and engineering roles.

## Programming Experience

Languages: Python, C/C++/C#, MATLAB ML Tools: tensorflow, scikit-learn, opency, pandas Misc: git, latex, mysql, mturk/php/html experiments

#### Education

2016 **Ph.D. in Psychology**, University of California, Berkeley.

Dissertation: Statistical models of learning and using semantic representations

Advisor: Thomas L. Griffiths

2010 M.Phil in Computer Science (CSTIT), University of Cambridge.

Thesis: Relevance feedback and novelty detection under the Bayesian Sets framework

Advisor: Zoubin Ghahramani

2009 B.A. (Honors) in Computer Science, New College of Florida.

Thesis: Temporal sequence analysis of Bottlenose dolphin vocalizations

Advisor: Heidi H. Harley

## Research Experience

2018–2020 **Postdoctoral Fellow**, University of Melbourne.

Complex Human Data Hub, PI: Charles Kemp

2017–2018 Postdoctoral Fellow, Max Planck Institute for Human Development.

Center for Adaptive Rationality, PI: Tim Pleskac

2010–2016 Graduate Student Researcher, University of California, Berkeley.

Computational Cognitive Science Lab, PI: Tom Griffiths

Language and Cognition Lab, PI: Terry Regier

Berkeley Artificial Intelligence Research (BAIR) Lab

2014 Visiting Scholar, Brown University.

Computational Cognitive Science Lab, PI: Joe Austerweil

2011 Graduate Summer School, University of California, Los Angeles.

Institute for Pure and Applied Mathematics (IPAM)

Probabilistic Models of Cognition: The Mathematics of Mind

2010 Graduate Summer School, Sardinia, Italy.

Machine Learning Summer School (MLSS)

Cognitive Science and Machine Learning

## Representative Publications and Conference Proceedings

- D.D. Bourgin, J.T. Abbott, and T.L. Griffiths. (in press). Recommendation as generalization: Using big data to evaluate cognitive models. *Journal of Experimental Psychology: General*.
- o J.C. Peterson, J.T. Abbott, and T.L. Griffiths. (2018). Evaluating (and improving) the correspondence between deep neural networks and human representations. *Cognitive Science*. 42(8), 2648-2669.
- A.E. Skelton, G. Catchpole, J.T. Abbott, J.M. Bosten, and A. Franklin. (2017). Biological origins of color categorization. *Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences*. 114(21), 5545-5550.
- D.D. Bourgin, J.T. Abbott, and T.L. Griffiths. (2017). Towards More Human-Like Recommendations. In Proceedings of the NIPS 2017 Workshop on Cognitively Informed Artificial Intelligence: Insights from Natural Intelligence. (Spotlight Presentation).
- E. Grant, J.C. Peterson, J.T. Abbott, S. Levine, T.L. Griffiths, and T. Darrell. (2017). Concept acquisition via meta-learning: Few-shot learning from positive examples. In *Proceedings of the NIPS 2017 Workshop on Cognitively Informed Artificial Intelligence: Insights from Natural Intelligence.*
- o J.T. Abbott, T.L. Griffiths, and T. Regier. (2016). Focal colors across languages are representative members of color categories. *Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences*. 113(40), 11178-11183.
- T.L. Griffiths, J.T. Abbott, and A.S. Hsu. (2016). Exploring human cognition using large image databases. *Topics in Cognitive Science*. 8(3), 569-588.
- J.C. Peterson, J.T. Abbott, and T.L. Griffiths. (2016). Adapting deep network features to capture psychological representations. In *Proceedings of the 38th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society*. (Computational Modeling Prize in Perception and Action).
- o J.T. Abbott, J.L. Austerweil, and T.L. Griffiths. (2015). Random walks on semantic networks can resemble optimal foraging. *Psychological Review*. 122(3), 558-569.
- Y. Jia, J.T. Abbott, J.L. Austerweil, T.L. Griffiths and T. Darrell. (2013). Visual concept learning: combining machine vision and Bayesian generalization on concept hierarchies. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 26.
- o J.T. Abbott, J.L. Austerweil, and T.L. Griffiths. (2012). Human memory search as a random walk in a semantic network. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 25*. (Spotlight Presentation).
- o J.T. Abbott, K.A. Heller, Z. Ghahramani, and T.L. Griffiths. (2011). Testing a Bayesian measure of representativeness using a large image database. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems* 24.
- J.T. Abbott and T.L. Griffiths. (2011). Exploring the influence of particle filter parameters on order effects in causal learning. In *Proceedings of the 33rd Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society*.

#### References

- Tom Griffiths
   Professor of Psychology and Computer Science
   Princeton University
   tomg@princeton.edu
- Charles Kemp
   Associate Professor of Psychological Sciences
   University of Melbourne
   c.kemp@unimelb.edu.au
- Terry Regier
   Professor of Linguistics and Cognitive Science
   University of California, Berkeley
   terry.regier@berkeley.edu